Mss.B.V462
American Philosophical Society
- Series II: Volumes, 3.0 Volume(s); Three volumes.; This series includes two commonplace books (1779; c. 1783), and one copybook with letters, dated 1784 to 1801.
  - Copybook, 1782-1801; D. [1] 22 [i.e.21] leaves in bound volume.
    - Letter to Henry Lawrence [sic], Charleston, June 23, 1789; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J.Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.17.) Forwards seeds. Introduces an artisar Mr. Dillet.
    - Letter to Benj[amin] Vaughan, London, July 13, 1789; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 2p. Copy. (see J.Vaughan. Copies of...letters,pp.14-15.) Concerning Hessian flies. Refers to B.Franklin. FILM54-65 FRAME190
    - Letter to Samuel Vaughan & Son, London, May 22, 1790; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 2p. Copy. (see J.Vaughan. Copies of...letters, pp.17-18.) Concerning commerce. Franklin's ideas on the subject. Concerning Washington's health. FILM 54-65 FRAME 189
    - Letter to Benj[ami]n Vaughan, London, April 16, 1791; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J.Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.18.) Concerning the possibility of a navigation act in the U.S.
    - Letter to Joseph Priestl[e]y, Birminghan, Aug. 2, 1791; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J. Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.19.) He has the confidence of the heads of government in the U.S. (Wording is faulty.)
    - Letter to Benj[ami]n Vaughan, London, Oct. 3, 1791; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J.Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.19.) Liberals must emigrate to the U.S. Concerning the Unitarians. Refers to Priestley.
    - Letter to Joseph Priestl[e]y, Birmingham, Oct. 3, 1791; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J. Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.20.) Sorry he is death with so badly in England. Has many good friends in the U.S.
    - Letter to Robert Fulton, New York, July 23, 1801; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J. Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.21.) Concerning his invention of the steam boat.
    - Letter to William Dunbar, Natchez, Dec. 10, 1801; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 2p. Copy. (see J. Vaughan. Copies of...letters, pp.21-221.) Concerning vaccination and Jefferson's part in it. Concerning C.W.Peale and the mammoth. The APS will appreciate any communication. The APS plans to keep a meteorological register.
    - Letter to W[illia]m Vaughan, London, June 2, undated; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 1p. Copy. (see J.Vaughan. Copies of...letters, p.4.) Lafayette seems to be doing more for making a treaty of commerce than the states.
- Series III: Estate Papers (Merrick), 1796-1822; B V462.m; 2 boxes; Papers relating to Vaughan's administration of the estate of Samuel Merrick, Philadelphia importer, 1796-1822.
  B V462.m
  This series includes papers relating to Vaughan's administration of the estate of Samuel Merrick, a Philadelphia importer of cloth. The items, which are dated between 1796 and 1822, deal with Vaughan’s efforts to settle Merrick’s accounts after his death in 1813. Many of the papers are receipts of shipments and similar records. There are also letters from and to various British merchants with whom Merrick was engaged in business. The items suggests that the settlement of Merrick’s estate was not an easy feat, not only because of Merrick’s poor bookkeeping habits, but also since the efforts to settle the accounts with British merchants coincided with the War of 1812. Of particular interest are the letters exchanged between Vaughan, Joseph Dixon, and Joseph Asquith, written during the war. Some of their letters deal with the interception of one of Dixon’s letters by an American privateer, and the subsequent publication of it in a New England newspaper, under the heading “Smuggling and Treason.” Also of interest are the letters by John Pershouse, who had volunteered as a security for Vaughan in the administration of Merrick's estate. Pershouse blamed Vaughan for a lawsuit brought by one of Merrick’s creditors, William Roberts.
  - Ledger leaf, 1796-1799; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
  - Bank book, 1796-1802; Volume with 12 leaves.; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    Bank book with the Bank of Pennsylvania.
  - Power of attorney to William Taylor, September 7, 1797; Roberts, Richard
    Manchester, Lancaster County, Great Britain; grants power of attorney to "adjust, liquidate and settle" accounts between Roberts and Merrick.
  - Power of attorney to Samuel Merrick, April 26, 1800; Printed form, filled in by hand.; Taylor, William
    Appoints Samuel Merrick as substitute and attorney for Richard Roberts.
  - Power of attorney to Samuel Merrick, July 2, 1798; Oastler, Joseph; Oastler, Richard; Oastler, Robert
    R., R., and J. Oates, of the County of Leeds, GB, appoint Samuel Merrick their deputy agent.
  - Power of attorney to Samuel Merrick, July 10, 1800; Printed form, filled in by hand; seals.; Taylor & Weston.
    File Plan note
    William Taylor and William Weston appoint Merrick their attorney.
  - Power of attorney to Samuel Merrick, July 16, 1800; Printed form, filled in by hand; seals.; Taylor, William
    W. Taylor, of Manchester, appoints Merrick his attorney.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, July 9, 1801; Oastler, Robert
    Business.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, July 10, 1801; Oastler, Robert
  - Estate of the late James Gramond in account with William Taylor, July 18, 1801
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, July 24, 1801; Oastler, Robert
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, June 17, 1802; Oastler, Robert
  - Power of attorney to Samuel Merrick, November 20, 1804; Four sheets, bound together.; Taylor, William; Weston, Samuel; Weston, William
    Also includes notary form, signed Robert Robson; affidavit, signed Matthew Thompson.
  - Letter to William Taylor, Jan. 14, 1805; Turner, J. E.; Turner, R.
    Regarding various accounts with American merchants. Also includes "Mr. William Fothergill in account with J.E & R. Turner."
    Item located in Oversize section.
    This item has been moved to the Oversized Materials section.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, August 17, 1805; Baker, William
    Is sending letters from Harris Leach & Co. and bill of exchange.
  - Power of attorney to Joseph Oastler, Oct. 20, 1806; Four leaves, bound together.; Oastler, Robert
    Also includes power of attorney to Samuel Merrick (March 17, 1807), and affidavits.
  - Power of attorney to Samuel Merrick, March 17, 1807; Printed form, filled in by hand.; Oastler, Joseph
  - Sales by Samuel Merrick on account and risque of Taylor, Weston & Co., 1807-1808; Four items.; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
  - Bank book, 1807-1809; Bound volume, 45 pages.; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    With the Bank of the U.S.
  - Note to John Vaughan, May 8, 1808; Printed form, filled in by hand.; United States Military Philosophical Society.
    West Point; signed Jon. Williams. Notification of election to membership. Includes constitution of Society.
  - Order to pay Joseph Dixon, March 25, 1811; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    Attached note says "will not be accepted, 21st May, 1811."
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, May 21, 1811; Taylor, William
    Regarding the collection of outstanding debts due to them.
  - Letter to William Taylor, July 18, 1811; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    Copy of a letter. Business. Concerning settlement of debts.
  - Protest of bill of Samuel Merrick by Taylor, Weston & Co., July 23, 1811; Denison, Joseph
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, October 5, 1811; Asquith, Joseph
  - Promissory notes to John Knight, Nov. 22, 1811; Eight notes.; Knight, Isaiah
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, Dec. 9, 1811; Oastler, Robert
    Received money, is anxious for further amounts.
  - Statement concerning case between Samuel Merrick and Isaiah Knight, 1811; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    In the Court of Common Pleas, March Term. Concerning Merrick's inability to collect money on a promissary note signed by Knight.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, July 13, 1812; Asquith, Joseph
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, July 15, 1812; Asquith, Joseph
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, Sep. 9, 1812; Frame, Anne
    Charles Town. Is sending money and asks his opinion respecting ordering goods this fall. Friendly letter.
  - Statement of accounts of Morrison & Rawle, Oct. 31, 1812; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
  - Receipts, 1812-1814; 14 items; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    Receipts paid for taxes, medical care (Dr. Physick), and expenses related to Merrick's funeral, including his coffin. Includes note stating Merrick's bank balance as of March 13, 1813.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, Jan. 13, 1813; Taylor, William
    Concerning accounts. Tells him to proceed in a "more Mercantile and Gentlemanly Manner."
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, Feb. 6, 1813; Burrill, James
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, Feb. 20, 1813; Ogden, Jonathan
    New York; enc. Business. Mentions Merrick's "Rheumatizm."
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, Feb. 24, 1813; Fragment.; Anonymous
    Incomplete letter on one side. On the other side are business notes, possinly regarding a shipment on the vessel Neptune.
  - Letter to James Burrill, February 1813; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    On the reverse is a letter to James Burrill, dated March 1813, crossed out.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, March 24, 1813; Ogden, Jonathan
    Regarding death of Samuel Merrick, and Merrick's debts.
  - Letter to English merchants, April 9, 1813; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Regarding estate of Samuel Merrick.
  - Letter to various firms, April 9, 1813; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Incl. copy for Mr. Vaughan. Letter of administration of estate. Refers to Act of Congress concerning goods that were shipped before the war.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, April 13, 1813; Burrill, James
    Regarding a bond that is due, asking for a remittance.
  - Receipts, May 26, 29, 1813; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    Three receipts from Merrick estate, signed Ellen Turner, M & C Stokes, Sarah Forde, Margaret Forde, J. Vaughan.
  - Letter to Joseph Lee, May 27, 1813; Burrill, James
    Requests that Vaughan remit him the advances he paid to S. Merrick.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, May 27, 1813; ALS, on printed form.; Thomas Robinson & Co..
    Regarding the prospect of war; will lend him their best "services, whether in peace or in War." Written on printed letter (May 22, 1813)describing recent arrival and prices of sugar, rum, coffee, etc., in Liverpool.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 11, 1813; Burrill, James
    Asking for reimbursement of advances.
  - Letter to Samuel Merrick, June 12, 1813; Thomas Robinson & Co..
    Regarding letters to Mr. Taylor. Comments on the possibility of peace. Written on printed letter (January 9, 1813) describing recent arrival and prices for sugar, coffee, cotton, etc., in Liverpool.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 21, 1813; Two items.; Dixon, Joseph
    Copies of six orders and shipments to Samuel Merrick, dated between January 7, 1811, and July 10, 1812. Notarized.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 22, 1813; Asquith, Joseph
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 22, 1813; Asquith, Joseph
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 22, 1813; Asquith, Joseph
  - Letter to John Vaughan, June 22, 1813; Dixon, Joseph
    Copies of four letters written by Joseph Asquith to Joseph Dixon regarding orders and shipments to Samuel Merrick, dated between December 10, 1810 and July 10, 1812. Notarized.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, September 9, 1813; Burrill, James
    Requests petition and documents regarding Merrick's case to be sent to him.
  - Sales at auction for account of Jonathan Ogden, September 14, 1813
    New York; list of cloth sold, with buyer and price listed.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, September 23, 1813; Ogden, Jonathan
    Enc. Is sending account of sales of "Bales of Woollens."
  - Letter to John Vaughan, September 27, 1813; Ogden, Jonathan
    Account of Sales of 4 Bales of Woollens, on account of Sam. Merrick.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, October 6, 1813; Burrill, James
    Is forwarding his account against Merrick.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, October 15, 1813; Ogden, Jonathan
    Regarding the four bales of Mr. Merrick's in the Neptune.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 8, 1813; Burrill, James
    Concerned that petition will be defeated. Asks Vaughan to use his influence to prevent it.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 20, 1813; Burrill, James
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 20, 1813; Dallas, Alexander James, 1759-1817
    Regarding a recent conversation about Merrick's case. Vaughan to present Merrick's orders to the Secretary of the Treasury "to remove every cause of suspicion." On same page is letter from John Vaughan to Dallas, Nov. 22, 1813.
  - Letter to William Jones, Nov. 22, 1813; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    To Secretary of the Treasury relative to Dixon's letter found on board an English vessel captured by an American privateer.
  - Letter to Joseph Dixon, November 22, 1813; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Scope and Contents note.
    Requests original letters by Merrick.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 27, 1813; U. S. Treasury Department
    ALS; signed William Jones. Does not suspect Vaughan of "any collusion or sanction," but suspicious of Dixon. Suspects that Merrick was the "mere Agent of Dixon." Is forwarding documents to district attorney.
  - Letter to ----, November (?) 1813; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Regarding publication of Dixon's letter in newspaper. Intends to publish statement of his own concern in the matter.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, December 9, 1813; Burrill, James
    Informs him that bond has been cancelled by order of Judge Story.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, December 20, 1813; Asquith, Joseph; Dixon, Joseph
    Hope that Mrs. Merrick and her son will find a business to support them, as they cannot import anything from England. Friendly letter.
  - Merrick estate. List of bad debts, [1813?]; Ledger (26 pp.; 21 pp. blank).; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    List of bad debts and losses as stated by Sam. Merrick in ledger, dated between 1798 and 1811. Also includes debts due from sundry persons not on Sam. Merrick's own account.
  - Letter to Secretary of the Treasury, [1813]; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Concerning publication of Dixon's letter in New England newspaper. Explains his connection to Merrick. Draft.
  - Letter to ----, [1813?]; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Is sending affidavit of J. Wilson, concering seizure and restoration of goods, and subsequent difficulty that arose due to incercepted letter from Dixon.
  - Memorandum, [1813?]; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Regarding Merrick's estate. Cannot find letterbook or copies of letters, account books are incomplete.
  - Payment made from Merrick estate, 1813-1822; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Concerning Merrick estate, 1813-1820; Four items.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Various accounts (paid and received), and calculations, concerning Merrick's estate.
  - Account of bonds due the customs, 1813; Two items.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Bonds due and bonds paid to Customs, for Merrick estate.
  - Memorandum, [1813?]; Two items.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Concerning debts acertained since Merrick's death.
  - Statement, March 9, 1814; Wilson, Job
    Verifies that letters are in Merrick's hand.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, March 11, 1814; Dixon, Joseph
    Is sending Merrick's letters with Job Wilson's affidavit of authenticity.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 2, 1814; Hainell, John
    Concerning the business between Merrick and Dixon. Mentions Dixon's letter and difficulty that arose from it.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Nov. 4, 1814; Howell, J.
    Mr. Webster is now at Mrs. Merricks house, wishes to see him regarding Dixon's business.
  - Letter to Joseph Dixon, Nov. 5, 1814; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Complaints about disrespectful treatment by one of Dixon's agents, "declines personal intercourse with them."
  - Letter to Warder & Brothers, Nov. 5, 1817; Oastler, Robert
    Wants his account with Merrick's estate brought to a conclusion.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, January 6, 1818; Warder & Brothers.
    Are enclosing letter from Robert Oastler.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, March 12, 1818; Warder & Brothers.
    Plan to settle his account soon. On same sheet is copy of letter from Robert Oastler to Warder & Brothers (Dec. 29, 1817).
  - Letter to John Vaughan, January 8, 1819; Rodney, A.
  - Statement of monies received, [1820?]; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Monies received from the estate of Merrick, from 1813 to 1819.
  - Settlement of Samuel Merrick's bank books, [ca. 1820]; Three items.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Covering period from Dec. 1813 to May 1822.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, December 31, 1821; Pershouse, John,1769-1841.
    Regarding Roberts' lawsuit of him as security to the Orphan's Court for the faithful discharge of Vaughan's duties as administrator of Merrick's estate.
  - Payments made to the Merrick estate, [1821]; Two items.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Covers period from May 1816 to 1821. Also includes "Ground Rent due before 13 March 1813."
  - Evidence, [1821]; Walker, James, Jr.
    Concerning business affairs. Refers to a trial, Samuel Merrick and Mr. Roberts.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, January 9, 1822; Pershouse, John,1769-1841.
    Concerning "the awful situation in which you have placed Mr. John Merrick and myself."
  - Letter to James Walker, Jr., January 22, 1822; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Concerning the suit brought by Roberts against administrators of Merrick's estate.
  - Letter to James Walker, Jr., January 22, 1822; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Copy of letter of same date.
  - Letter to James Walker, Jr., January 22, 1822; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letter to John Vaughan, May 17, 1822; Roberts, William, Jr.
    Is requesting book of account between him and Merrick for inspection. Requests information whether Merrick held shares in certain businesses.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, July 19, 1822; Pershouse, John,1769-1841.
    Regarding the security he expected to get from Vaughan.
  - Expenses on Merrick's house, [1822]; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Paid by administrators for the period 1813 to 1822.
  - Memoranda, undated; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Not located 6/2010.
  - Invoices of shipments of cloth, undated; c. 75 loose items, various sizes, including six printed form, filled in by hand, and one newspaper clipping.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Receipts and notes re shipments of cloth from England to Samuel Merrick in Philadelphia, listing type of cloth, date, purchaser, cost. Includes payments received after Merrick's death. Newspaper clipping of Joseph Dixon's letter.
  - Shipments, etc., on account of Taylor Weston & Co., undated; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
  - Index to account book, undated; Four leaves, bound.; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
  - Various accounts and calculations, undated; 31 loose items, various sizes.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
- Series IV: Photocopies (Du Pont), 1801-1816; Correspondence with Pierre, E. I., and Victor Marie du Pont, 1801-1816, when Vaughan served as agent for their company.; Photostats of 73 letters.
  B V462.4
  Eleutherian Mills Historical Library
  - Letters to Du Pont & Co., 1817-1818; 14 letters; Dahlgren, Bernard; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to John Vaughan, April 1807; Feb. 22, 1819; undated; 3 letters; Du Pont family
  - Accounts with Du Pont & Co., undated; 7 items
  - Letter to Du Pont & Co., Dec. 15, 1818; Dahlgren, Bernard; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to Du Pont & Co., 1817-1834; 7 items.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Includes printed letter to the public asking for support for the "Pennsylvania Institution for the Instruction of the Blind."
  - Letters to Du Pont & Co, 1802; 3 letters; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to Du Pont & Co., Wilmington, 1804-1825; 20 items; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to Victor Du Pont, consul, 1796-1826; 9 letters; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to and from Piere Samuel Du Pont de Nemours, New York, 1802-1816; 8 items; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to Victor Du Pont & Co., New York, 1802-1803; 4 items; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letters to Du Pont & Co., Wilmington, 1818; 2 items; Dahlgren, Bernard; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
- E. W. Madeira Notes on John Vaughan, 1778-1936; 1 box
  - Folder 1, 1935-1936
  - Folder 2 - Philadelphia 1782-1783. John Vaughan correspondence with William Temple Franklin.
  - Folder 3 - Letters between John Vaughan and Thomas Jefferson., 1820-1936
  - Folder 4 - John Vaughan correspondence., 1944-1945
  - Folder 5 - John Vaughan - Historical data, 1792-1940
  - Folder 6 - Correspondence, 1933-1935
  - Folder 7 - Preliminary, 1756-1778
  - Folder 8 - Vaccination and Jefferson letters, 1792-1940
  - Folder 9 - France, 1778-1782
  - Folder 10 - London, 1783